Inequality for All is a documentary film directed by Jacob Kornbluth.
Based on Reich's 2010 book Aftershock: The Next Economy and America's Future, the
film examines widening income inequality in the United States.
Labor Secretary Robert Reich tries to raise awareness
of the country's widening economic gap.
He publicly argued about the issue for decades, and producing a film
of his viewpoints was a "final frontier" for him.
In addition to being a social issue documentary, Inequality for All is also partially a biopic regarding
Reich's early life and his time as Secretary of Labor under Bill Clinton's presidency.
Warren Buffett and Nick Hanauer, two entrepreneurs and investors in the top 1%, are interviewed in the film, supporting
Reich's belief in an economy that benefits all citizens, including those of the middle and lower classes.
Self, played by Robert Reich.
Doralee Rhodes (archive footage), played by Dolly Parton.
Mary Beth Lacey (archive footage), played by Tyne Daly.
Violet Newstead (archive footage), played by Lily Tomlin.
Mary Richards (archive footage), played by Mary Tyler Moore.
Murphy Brown (archive footage), played by Candice Bergen.
Inequality for All is a 2013 documentary film directed by Jacob Kornbluth and
narrated by American economist, author and professor Robert Reich.
Based on Reich's 2010 book Aftershock: The Next Economy and America's Future, the
film examines widening income inequality in the United States.
Reich publicly argued about the issue for decades, and producing a
film of his viewpoints was a "final frontier" for him.
In addition to being a social issue documentary, Inequality for All is also partially a biopic regarding
Reich's early life and his time as Secretary of Labor under Bill Clinton's presidency.
Warren Buffett and Nick Hanauer, two entrepreneurs and investors in the top 1%, are interviewed in the film, supporting
Reich's belief in an economy that benefits all citizens, including those of the middle and lower classes.
As shown via a series of suspension bridge graphs, the income gap between middle-to-low-class Americans and the top 1% in
the United States was at the same extreme highs in 1928 and 2007, two years that preceded economic crashes.
Reich argues that inequality in capitalism is a necessary incentive for citizens to work harder, but at a low-enough level to where democracy is protected and is in a virtuous cycle;
with high-enough wages and taxes, there will be more investments in government programs, a more college-educated population, and consumer spending creating more jobs.
The United States economy was in this cycle in the 1940s and 1970s, but that changed starting in the late 1970s as a result of union-busting, tax cuts, deregulation, job outsourcing, and other
changes in the system meant to increase Wall Street's profits; this resulted in a decline of average worker pay and an increased amount of average income for top-earners from 1978 to 2010.
Inequality for All premiered at the 2013 Sundance Film Festival in the Documentary Competition section that had
several other political films in its line-up, including another film about income inequality.
It won the festival's U.S.
Documentary Special Jury Award for Achievement in Filmmaking and was
bought by RADiUS-TWC five days after its January 19 premiere.
After months of running at several other festivals, the film was released to United States theaters by RADiUS on September
27, 2013 and grossed more than $1 million in just over a month, which was rare for an issue documentary.
It received very high opinions from professional critics, who praised its easy-to-understand demonstration of a complicated topic and likeable narrator; however, it also garnered
criticism for what libertarian and right-leaning sources and publications deemed to be narrow-minded, unoriginal viewpoints and lack of credible opposing arguments.
The film explores themes of upper class, middle
class, economics, inequality, poor.